I’m often asked
what my opinion
about a diet
or disease is.
Who cares what my or
anyone else’s opinion is.
All we should care about
is what the science says.
What does the best available
balance of evidence
Published in the peer-
reviewed medical literature
have to say right now?
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Our story today is about
an alternative approach
to some of the health
problems that bother us.
And we start with the unusual
powers of garden variety lettuce.
There is a perception that time
spent asleep is time wasted,
but it is widely recognized that
inadequate sleep is associated
with multiple acute
and chronic conditions,
and results in the increased
risk of death and disease.
Force people to go one week with
only six hours of sleep a night,
and you can change expression
of more than 700 genes.
The most dire effect may
be endothelial dysfunction.
The endothelium is the thin layer of
cells that covers the internal surface
of blood vessels and is responsible
for allowing our arteries
to relax and dilate
back open properly.
Randomize people for about a week
to get five rather than seven hours
of sleep, and just that two-hour
difference a night resulted
in a significant impairment
in artery function.
Okay, but what do these numbers mean?
How bad is a week of 5-hour nights?
Sleep deprivation is no joke.
The magnitude of impairment is similar
to that reported in people who smoke,
have diabetes, or have
coronary artery disease.
No wonder people who sleep less than
seven hours a night may experience
a 12% to 35% increased
risk of premature death
compared to those who
get a full seven hours.
Yet a significant proportion
of the population may
routinely get less than that.
Sufficiently long, restful
sleep sessions each night
are said to be an indisputable
cornerstone of good health.
Okay, so what can we do about it?
Those who have sleep apnea,
a common consequence of obesity
that interferes with sleep, benefit
from the use of CPAP machines
while they're losing the weight to treat
the underlying cause, hopefully.
But what if apnea isn't your problem?
What if you just have trouble
falling asleep or staying asleep?
Any natural dietary remedies?
I already have videos on using
kiwifruit to fight insomnia,
and tart cherries, too.
Are there any vegetables
that might help?
Lactuca sativa is a plant that
has been traditionally used
in the treatment of insomnia.
What is this exotic sounding
leafy vegetable? Lettuce!
Evidently lettuce extracts have been
used from the time of the Roman Empire
as agents with sedative and
sleep-inducing properties.
Lettuce actually does have a hypnotic
substance in it called lactucin,
which is what makes
lettuce taste a little bitter.
But you don't know if it actually
works until you put it to the test.
And it works...in toads.
But it also works in rodents.
Sleep in both mice and rats
is enhanced by romaine lettuce.
They used romaine since
it has a higher lactucin content
compared to other lettuces.
Okay, but does it work in people?
About 10 years ago, a study was
published in which insomnia sufferers
were randomized to receive lettuce seed
oil, oil extracted from lettuce seeds.
Within a week, about 70% of those
in the lettuce seed oil group
said their insomnia very much
or much improved,
compared to only 20% in
the placebo control group.
The researchers concluded that lettuce
seed oil was found to be a useful,
safe sleeping aid in geriatric patients
suffering from sleeping difficulties.
They chose to study older individuals
because insomnia affects surprisingly
20 to 40% of older adults
at least a few nights a month.
You think that's bad. Sleep
disturbances can plague as many
as nearly 8 out of 10 women
during pregnancy.
Of course, there's lots
of different sleeping pills,
but they may endanger
the fetus or mother.
For example, doctors frequently
prescribe Ambien for pregnant women
who have trouble sleeping, but Ambien
use is associated with a wide range
of adverse pregnancy outcomes
like low birth weight babies,
premature birth, and cesarean section.
And the use of valium during
pregnancy has been linked
to birth defects
including limb deficiencies.
There has to be a better way.
What about trying lettuce?
The lettuce oil study had
a number of limitations.
For example, it was only single-blind,
meaning the researchers knew
who was on the lettuce supplements
and who was on placebo,
which could have introduced some bias.
But the researchers essentially said,
"Give us a break. Big pharma
has billions to spend on research.
No one wants to fund
studies on lettuce."
Finally, we got a double-blind,
placebo-controlled study,
but this time on a whole food,
not just a lettuce seed extract.
Yeah, but how to you come
up with a placebo lettuce?
How are you going hide who
gets lettuce and who doesn't?
Well, you can't fit a head
of lettuce into a capsule,
but you can fit whole
lettuce seeds.
And here we go: a double-blind
randomized placebo-controlled trial
on lettuce seeds for
pregnancy-related insomnia.
A hundred pregnant women
with insomnia were randomized
to receive capsules containing
either a quarter teaspoon
of ground lettuce seeds or
a placebo for two weeks,
and those on the lettuce seeds
saw a significant improvement
in a sleep quality index score
compared to placebo
with no reported side effects.
In our final story today,
we look at how cranberries
and pumpkin seeds
may help with an
enlarged prostate.
More than 50% of men in their 50s
and 70% or more of men in their 60s
suffer from benign prostatic
hypertrophy or BPH,
otherwise known
as enlarged prostate.
This can result in burdensome
lower urinary tract symptoms
such as having to get up
frequently at night to pee.
Current medical treatments are
clinically effective, but their efficacy
is compromised by side effects
and low compliance rates.
Symptoms include sexual dysfunction,
high-grade prostate cancer,
and depression. No wonder
there's poor compliance.
And when medication treatment fails,
surgical procedures are considered,
such as transurethral
resection of the prostate.
There has got to be a better way.
Population studies suggest
that low intake of animal protein
and high intake of fruits and
vegetables may be protective,
but not just cutting down
on any animal protein.
Eggs and poultry seem to be the
worst, along with refined grains,
but no association was found
for red meat or dairy.
Population studies aside, are there any
foods that have been put to the test?
There have been more than 30
randomized controlled trials
on the herb saw palmetto, and it's
been found to be totally useless.
Evidently, cranberries were used
by Native Americans to treat
urinary ailments, but you don't
know until you put 'em to the test.
Now, when they say dried cranberries,
they're not talking about those sugary,
oily craisins, but rather just
straight, whole cranberry powder.
And significant improvements were
seen in BPH symptoms, quality of life,
and all urination parameters
for just about a teaspoon a day
of powdered cranberries.
So we know a teaspoon works,
but what about a third of a teaspoon
or a sixth of a teaspoon?
They also helped.
Now this study used a supplement
because it was funded by
the supplement company,
but the supplement is just
straight cranberry powder,
so you might as well buy it
in bulk for much cheaper
and just add it to a
smoothie or something.
What about using a berry
that's a little tastier,
like drinking purple grape juice?
No benefit whatsoever.
In a previous video, I talked
about the use of flaxseeds,
which may have a therapeutic
efficacy comparable to that
of commonly used drugs,
with only good side effects.
Okay, so what about other seeds?
Pumpkin seeds have evidently
been used in folk medicine
as a remedy for prostate
disorders for centuries,
and in a petri dish, they can cut the
growth of BPH prostate cells in half.
Scientists have also injected
pumpkin seed extracts into rabbits,
but what about people?
Pumpkin seed oil appears
to help with prostate issues.
When pitted head-to-head
against the drug Prazosin,
it seemed to work
as well as the pill.
The same when it was head-to-head
against the drug Terazosin.
What they didn't have though
was a placebo group.
It would have been nice to see how
well the pumpkin seed oil supplements
did against placebo, and hey,
in an ideal world, I'd love to also see
a group just given whole
pumpkin seeds themselves,
and boom: there it is. More than
a thousand men were randomized
to either a pumpkin seed
extract, a placebo,
or just about a tablespoon
a day of plain pumpkin seeds.
The study was funded by the drug
company that made the supplement,
but the supplement flopped,
it was no better than placebo,
but the pumpkin seeds
themselves worked.
The supplement appeared to reduce
symptoms, but not better than placebo.
However, just the plain old seeds did.
So it wasn't just some compound
extracted from the oil.
And, in fact, we've since learned that
even an oil-free extract seemed to work.
Bottom line, the researchers concluded,
is that pumpkin seed could be
recommended for BPH patients
with mild-to-moderate symptoms.
This conclusion was echoed by the
European equivalent of the FDA.
Pumpkin seeds can be used for the
relief of lower urinary tract symptoms
related to an enlarged prostate
after more serious conditions
have been excluded
by a medical doctor.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite to each of these topics.
For a timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my last book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my second-to-last book,
my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.